[Music]
foreign
Medical Association started warning
people about excess sugar consumption
over 75 years ago based in part on our
understanding that you know sugar
supplies nothing and nutrition but
calories and the vitamins provided by
other foods are sapped by sugar to
liberate those calories hence added
sugars aren't just empty calories but
like negative nutrition the more added
sugars one consumes the more
nutritionally depleted one may become
given the totality of scientific
evidence the FDA decided to make
processed food manufacturers declare
added sugars on the nutrition facts
label the national yogurt Association
was livid opposing the added Sugar's
declaration since they needed added
sugars to increase their product's
palatability the junk food Association
questioned the science
whereas the ice cream folks seem to
imply consumers would be too stupid to
use it so better leave it off
the world's biggest cereal company
Kellogg took a similar tact opposing it
so as not to confuse the consumer and
should the FDA proceed with such
labeling against their objections added
sugar should at most be communicated in
a footnote
see the goal is to provide consumers
with useful information so they can make
informed choices
this from a company that describes their
Fruit Loops is packed with delicious
fruity taste fruity Aroma bright colors
made with whole grains and lightly
sweetened a good source of fiber lightly
sweetened Fruit Loops has more sugar
than a Krispy Kreme donut
Fruit Loops is more than 40 Sugar by
weight
the tobacco industry use similar terms
like Light low mild to make their
products appear healthier before they
were recently barred from doing so now
sugar interests are fighting similar
battles over whether they're healthy
natural a lightly sweetened terminology
is similarly deceptive but just look at
all those vitamins and minerals they
added that was one of the ways the
cereal companies responded
to calls for Banning sugary cereals
General Mills defended the likes of
Frankenberry tricks and Lucky Charms for
being fortified with essential vitamins
sir grape fellow I Learned was a grape
flavored cereal complete with sweet
great star bit marshmallows but don't
worry it was a vitamin charged sugary
breakfast cereal said Dr Jean Mayer from
Harvard are not a complete food even
fortified with you know eight or ten
vitamins I think your point is well
taken replied Senator McGovern these
products may be mislabeled press more
correctly called candy vitamins than
cereals
Plastering nutrient claims on the box
can create a nutritional facade acting
to distract attention away from unsavory
quality such as excess sugar content the
majority of parents have been found to
misinterpret the meaning of claims
commonly used on children's cereals
raising significant public health
concerns
ironically cereal boxes bearing low
calorie claims were found to have more
calories on average than without such a
claim so it's like that the cereal doth
protest too much
even candy bar companies are getting in
on the action bragging about their
protein content because it has some
peanuts or something but it's also a
candy bar with 50 grams of sugar you
know just like you know Fruit Loops
could be considered breakfast candy is
the same serving would have 40.
given research suggesting consumers
believe front of package claims perceive
them to be you know government endorsed
and use them to ignore the nutrition
facts panel on the back there's been a
call from nutrition professionals to
consider an outlight ban on all
front-of-package claims the industry
short-lived smart choices label was met
with disbelief when it was found
adorning qualifying cereals like fruit
loops Cookie Crisp the process food
industry spent more than a billion
dollars lobbying against the adoption of
more informative labeling a traffic
light approach railing against the
suggestion that any food might be too
high in anything
oh